<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="000109000000000" Lemma="ἀήρ" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="true" AlphaPos="α">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G0109</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes>
    <Note Caller="1" LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="" LastEditedBy="">
      <References/>
      <Content>It would be possible to combine the meanings of ἀήρ[a] ({D:1.6}) and ἀήρ[c] ({D:1.7}) under a single generic definition of space above the earth. One could then leave it to the context to specify the particular area referred to. However, because of the relationship of ἀήρ[a] to the meaning of οὐρανός[a] ({D:1.5}) and the fact that in so many languages a distinct contrast in meaning is preserved for expressions designating the sky in contrast with the area immediately above the surface of the earth, it seems better to make a distinction at this point.</Content>
    </Note>
  </Notes>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="000109001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, m.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="ἀήρ" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-έρος</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="000109001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="1.6" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Geographical Objects and Features</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Regions Above the Earth</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-03-05 22:04:46" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>the space immediately above the earths surface, and not including the dome arching over the earth</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>air</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>The expression εἰς ἀέρα λαλοῦντες, literally ‘talking into the air,’ may be regarded as a type of idiom meaning ‘talking to no purpose’ or ‘talking without anyone understanding.’ Accordingly, ἔσεσθε γὰρ εἰς ἀέρα λαλοῦντες may be rendered as ‘you will be talking, but no one will understand’ or ‘you will be talking, but your words will not enter anyone.’ In {S:04402202300026}, κονιορτὸν βαλλόντων εἰς τὸν ἀέρα ‘throwing dust into the air,’ it may be more appropriate in a number of languages to say ‘throwing dust above themselves’ or simply ‘throwing dust up.’ A literal rendering of ‘throwing dust into the air’ might suggest in some languages that the air was some kind of a container in which the dust remained.|The Greek term ἀήρ in {S:06600900200046} (ἐσκοτώθη ὁ ἥλιος καὶ ὁ ἀὴρ ἐκ τοῦ καπνοῦ τοῦ φρέατος ‘the sun and the air were darkened by the smoke from the pit’) may very well be translated as ‘air,’ but since it is a reference primarily to space rather than to substance, it is more natural in a number of languages to say ‘the sky was darkened by the smoke from the pit.’</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04402202300026</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04601400900038</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>05200401700036</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>06600900200046</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>06601601700020</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
        <LEXMeaning Id="000109001002000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="2.2" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Natural Substances</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Air</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-03-05 22:04:46" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>air as an elemental substance</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>air</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>οὕτως πυκτεύω ὡς οὐκ ἀέρα δέρων ‘I do not box like someone hitting the air’ {S:04600902600024}. In some languages it may be quite impossible to translate literally ‘hitting the air,’ for since the air is not regarded as a kind of material substance, it is impossible to hit it. The closest equivalent may be ‘hitting nothing’ or possibly ‘as though hitting something.’</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04600902600024</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
        <LEXMeaning Id="000109001003000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="1.7" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Geographical Objects and Features</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Regions Above the Earth</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-03-05 22:04:46" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>the space above the earth inhabited by and under the control of certain supernatural powers{N:001}</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>air</Gloss>
                <Gloss>sky</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>In the context of {S:04900200200034} ἐξουσία is best understood as a collective and thus referring to the various supernatural powers regarded as inhabiting the area above the earth and thus controlling in many respects both the behavior and the fate of people. See also {D:12.44}.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04900200200034</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
        <LEXMeaning Id="000109001004000" IsBiblicalTerm="Y" EntryCode="12.44" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Supernatural Beings and Powers</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Supernatural Powers</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXCollocations>
            <LEXCollocation>ἄρχων τῆς ἐξουσίας τοῦ ἀέρος</LEXCollocation>
          </LEXCollocations>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-03-05 22:04:46" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>(title for supernatural forces and powers) a supernatural power having some particular role in controlling the destiny and activities of human beings</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>power</Gloss>
                <Gloss>authority</Gloss>
                <Gloss>lordship</Gloss>
                <Gloss>ruler</Gloss>
                <Gloss>wicked force</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>Some scholars have believed that it is possible to reconstruct at least in part some of the hierarchy represented by these various supernatural forces and powers, on the basis of the neoplatonic system of nine such powers arranged in three orders of three each. NT terminology and usage does not, however, lend itself to such a classification, and it is difficult, if not impossible, to determine what are the significant differences between these supernatural powers and forces.|For the most part, translators have endeavored to render the various terms in somewhat different ways, for example, ἐξουσία as ‘authority’; δύναμις as ‘power’; κυριότης as ‘ruler’; and phrases such as τὰ πνευματικὰ τῆς πονηρίας ἐν τοῖς ἐπουρανίοις as ‘wicked spiritual forces in the heavenly world.’ In a number of languages, however, there are simply not enough terms to designate various kinds of powers, authorities, and forces which could be employed in speaking of such supernatural impersonal powers. Accordingly, some translators have simply used a phrase such as ‘any and all kinds of supernatural powers.’ Where it is possible to make certain lexical distinctions between terms and phrases, this, of course, should be done, but in a number of contexts this may be impossible, and accordingly, some explanation in a marginal note may be required if the reader is to understand satisfactorily the intent of the passages in question.|In some instances a measure of meaning may be obtained by somewhat paraphrastic expressions. For example, {S:04900200200034} is rendered in some languages as ‘at that time you lived in the way in which the spirit that governs this world dictated you should live. This is the way the one who rules over the power in space commanded you to live. This is the very spirit that now commands the people who disobey God.’</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04900200200034</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>