<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="000256000000000" Lemma="ἀλώπηξ" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="true" AlphaPos="α">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G0258</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes/>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="000256001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, f.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="ἀλώπηξ" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-εκος</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="000256001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="4.10" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Animals</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Animals</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-05-26 14:35:44" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>animal looking like a longhaired dog with a pointed nose and a bushy tail; either reddish with white underparts (fox) or yellowish brown with red tips to the fur on the back (jackal); scavenger; associated with destruction and devastation, and also with being insignificant but self-important; also intelligent and quick-witted, crafty</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>fox</Gloss>
                <Gloss>jackal</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>Though the Greek term ἀλώπηξ and the corresponding Hebrew terms used in the OT may refer to either a fox or a jackal, ἀλώπηξ in the NT seems to refer primarily to a fox (see Fauna and Flora of the Bible, pp. 31-32, for certain significant distinctions between foxes and jackals).|In areas of the world where the fox is not known, one can sometimes speak of ‘a small wild dog’ or ‘an animal like a small wild dog.’ In other instances translators have borrowed the term ‘fox’ from a dominant language in the area and have then explained the appearance and habits of the animal in a glossary.|For ἀλώπηξ in a figurative sense as applied by Jesus to Herod Antipas, see {D:88.120}.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04000802000014</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04200905800014</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXLinks>
            <LEXLink>fauna:2.22</LEXLink>
          </LEXLinks>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
        <LEXMeaning Id="000256001002000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="88.120" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Moral and Ethical Qualities and Related Behavior</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Bad, Evil, Harmful, Damaging</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-05-26 14:35:44" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>(a figurative extension of meaning of {L:ἀλώπηξ&lt;SDBG:ἀλώπηξ:000000&gt;}[a] ‘fox,’ {D:4.10}) a wicked person, probably with the implication of being cunning and treacherous</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>wicked person</Gloss>
                <Gloss>cunning person</Gloss>
                <Gloss>fox</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>Some scholars, however, suggest that ἀλώπηξ in {S:04201303200014} may imply ‘worthlessness.’|Rendering ἀλώπηξ in {S:04201303200014} by a term meaning ‘fox’ may sometimes be misleading, since in some cultures the fox is regarded as a particularly wise animal, and therefore referring to a person as a fox may be a compliment. A local term for ‘fox’ may have other connotations which are quite undesirable. For example, in some languages a term for fox is used to designate a male or female prostitute, usually of the lowest grade.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04201303200014</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>