<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="001537000000000" Lemma="εἰσδέχομαι" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="true" AlphaPos="ε">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G1523</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes>
    <Note Caller="1" LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="" LastEditedBy="">
      <References/>
      <Content>There are no doubt certain contextual constraints involved in the choice of ἀναδέχομαι[a], ἀποδέχομαι[a], ἐπιδέχομαι[a], εἰσδέχομαι, ὑποδέχομαι, προσδέχομαι[b], and παραδέχομαι[b] in the sense that the spacial relationships involved in the welcoming of a guest can be reflected in the prepositional prefixes. For example, in {S:04200804000014} the use of ἀποδέχομαι may focus upon the particular source, while ἐπιδέχομαι in {S:06400101000044} may be relevant in view of the fact that the believers are coming to a particular point. προσδέχομαι in {S:04201500200026} may suggest a kind of reciprocal relationship which is established with outcasts, and παραδέχομαι in {S:04401500400010} may simply point to spacial proximity. However, it would be wrong to insist upon clear distinctions in meaning based on the very limited number of contexts involved. Some of these same distinctions in spacial relations may exist for the set προσλαμβάνω[e], παραλαμβάνω[d], ἀπολαμβάνω[d].</Content>
    </Note>
  </Notes>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="001537001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>verb</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <RelatedLemmas>
        <RelatedLemma>
          <Word>δέχομαι</Word>
        </RelatedLemma>
      </RelatedLemmas>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="001537001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="34.53" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Association</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Welcome, Receive</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-10-27 02:54:43" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>to accept the presence of a person with friendliness{N:001}</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>to welcome</Gloss>
                <Gloss>to receive</Gloss>
                <Gloss>to accept</Gloss>
                <Gloss>to have as a guest</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>In view of the fact that εἰσδέχομαι in {S:04700601700030} refers to God’s receiving people, it may be necessary to use quite a different expression than one would normally employ in referring to welcoming a guest into the home. In some instances one may use a rather generic expression such as ‘to accept,’ and this may be expressed idiomatically in some languages as ‘to extend my hand to you’ or ‘to count you as belonging to me.’ It is the figurative usage of εἰσδέχομαι in this type of context which may lead to a somewhat different type of rendering.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04700601700030</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>