<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="001789000000000" Lemma="ἐνορκίζω" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="false" AlphaPos="ε">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G3726a</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes>
    <Note Caller="1" LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="" LastEditedBy="">
      <References/>
      <Content>It is possible that ὁρκίζω, ἐνορκίζω, and ἐξορκίζω differ slightly in meaning, but this cannot be determined on the basis of available contexts.</Content>
    </Note>
  </Notes>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="001789001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>verb</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <RelatedLemmas>
        <RelatedLemma>
          <Word>ὁρκίζω</Word>
        </RelatedLemma>
      </RelatedLemmas>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="001789001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="Y" EntryCode="33.467" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Communication</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Swear, Put Under Oath, Vow</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-06-01 10:23:56" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>to demand that a person take an oath as to the truth of what is said or as to the certainty that one will carry out the request or command{N:001}</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>to put under oath</Gloss>
                <Gloss>to insist that one take an oath</Gloss>
                <Gloss>to require that one swear</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>It is extremely difficult to translate ὁρκίζω, ἐνορκίζω, and ἐξορκίζω in a literal manner, though in some contexts one can say ‘I put you under oath,’ but in a number of passages the person speaking is imploring and not necessarily in a position to command or insist. Therefore, in a passage such as {S:04100500700032}, one may render the meaning idiomatically as ‘for God’s sake, I ask you, do not punish me.’ In {S:05200502700002} one may translate ‘in the name of the Lord, I ask you to read this letter to all the Christian brothers,’ and in {S:04002606300020} one may translate ‘in the name of the living God, I charge you, Tell us who you are.’|In most languages one may translate ὁρκίζω, ἐνορκίζω, and ἐξορκίζω by simply adding a causative component to terms meaning ‘to swear’ or ‘to take an oath.’ In other words, ὁρκίζω, ἐνορκίζω, and ἐξορκίζω may be rendered as ‘to cause a person to say under oath.’</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>05200502700002</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>