<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="002071000000000" Lemma="ἐρίφιον" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="true" AlphaPos="ε">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G2055</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes>
    <Note Caller="1" LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="" LastEditedBy="">
      <References/>
      <Content>With a number of diminutive forms for animals there may be connotative meanings of endearment or special appreciation, but it is difficult to establish such values in the case of most contexts.</Content>
    </Note>
  </Notes>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="002071001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, n.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="ἐρίφιον" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-ου</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <RelatedLemmas>
        <RelatedLemma>
          <Word>ἔριφος</Word>
        </RelatedLemma>
      </RelatedLemmas>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="002071001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="4.19" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Animals</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Animals</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-07-02 09:39:03" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>(the diminutive of ἔριφος but without special diminutive meaning{N:001}) kid, he-goat in the singular and goats in the plural (in the plural form both male and female goats are included in the reference)</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>kid</Gloss>
                <Gloss>he-goat</Gloss>
                <Gloss>goat</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>Since goats are so widely distributed throughout the world, there is usually little or no difficulty involved in finding a satisfactory term. The difficulty arises, however, in the connotations of the term for goat, especially in contrast with sheep. In contrast with usage in the Bible, in many parts of the tropical world goats are much more highly prized than sheep, because they can forage well for themselves and are appreciated for their meat. Sheep, on the other hand, are often regarded as scavengers and are much less valued. One should not reverse biblical statements about sheep and goats, but marginal notes and a fuller explanation of cultural differences in a glossary are important.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04002503300022</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXLinks>
            <LEXLink>fauna:2.16.1</LEXLink>
          </LEXLinks>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>