<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="002579000000000" Lemma="κάμηλος" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="true" AlphaPos="κ">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G2574</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes/>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="002579001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, f.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="κάμηλος" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-ου</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="002579001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="4.30" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Animals</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Animals</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-09-10 11:47:49" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>large quadruped mammal; Camelus dromedarius and Camelus bactrianus; bactrians may reach 2 m.; dromedaries are bigger and a uniform light fawn color; bactrians are darker; suited to life in desert areas; store excess food in their humps, can go without water for long periods; can make long journeys through dry areas; used for riding and for carrying heavy loads and pulling carts; hair woven into cloth used for making tents or outer robes; milk used as food and drink; symbol of wealth and commerce</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>camel</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>In most areas where camels are not known, a term for ‘camel’ has been borrowed from a dominant language. In other instances people may have constructed descriptive phrases. For example, in Timorese the first two expressions suggested for camel were ‘the horse with a crooked back’ or ‘the long-legged horse,’ but finally people settled upon a more satisfactory rendering, namely, ‘the horse of the desert.’ In a number of languages a camel is simply called ‘the big humped animal.’ In a number of cases, however, it may be useful to have some kind of a description of a camel in a glossary or word list.|In referring to the camel’s hair garment worn by John the Baptist, there are two problems. In the first place, it is important to translate the phrase ‘garment of camel’s hair’ in such a way as to indicate that the garment was made of cloth woven out of camel’s hair and did not consist of the entire skin nor of camel’s hair stuck onto John the Baptist’s body. In the second place, it is important to indicate that this camel’s hair garment was a kind of rough garment, since in a number of languages an expression such as ‘camel’s hair coat’ would refer to an expensive, luxury garment. See also {D:6.216}.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04000300400022</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04001902400014</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04002302400018</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04100100600014</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04101002500006</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04201802500008</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXLinks>
            <LEXLink>fauna:2.8</LEXLink>
          </LEXLinks>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>