<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="002980000000000" Lemma="κυριότης" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="false" AlphaPos="κ">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G2963</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes/>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="002980001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, f.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="κυριότης" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-ητος</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <RelatedLemmas>
        <RelatedLemma>
          <Word>κυριεύω</Word>
        </RelatedLemma>
      </RelatedLemmas>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="002980001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="Y" EntryCode="37.52" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Control, Rule</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Rule, Govern</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-10-29 10:31:42" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>(derivative of {L:κύριος&lt;SDBG:κύριος:000002&gt;}[c] ‘one who rules,’ {D:37.51}) a supernatural ruling power</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>ruling power</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>In general, the series of terms θρόνοι, κυριότητες, ἀρχαί, and ἐξουσίαι in {S:05100101600052} (as well as in {S:04900102100018}) are understood as being supernatural cosmic powers, whether angelic or demonic (see {D:12.44}), but it is possible that these should be understood in terms of human rulers.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04900102100018</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>05100101600044</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>06100201000022</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>06500100800018</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
        <LEXMeaning Id="002980001002000" IsBiblicalTerm="Y" EntryCode="12.44" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Supernatural Beings and Powers</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Supernatural Powers</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-10-29 10:31:42" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>(title for supernatural forces and powers) a supernatural power having some particular role in controlling the destiny and activities of human beings</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>power</Gloss>
                <Gloss>authority</Gloss>
                <Gloss>lordship</Gloss>
                <Gloss>ruler</Gloss>
                <Gloss>wicked force</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>Some scholars have believed that it is possible to reconstruct at least in part some of the hierarchy represented by these various supernatural forces and powers, on the basis of the neoplatonic system of nine such powers arranged in three orders of three each. NT terminology and usage does not, however, lend itself to such a classification, and it is difficult, if not impossible, to determine what are the significant differences between these supernatural powers and forces.|In the case of {S:04900102100018} some scholars apply the terms in question both to the supernatural and to the human sphere, thus emphasizing the totality of Christ’s rule. This has a considerable measure of justification in view of the concepts held by persons in the ancient world, since various earthly powers were supposed to reflect corresponding supernatural powers.|For the most part, translators have endeavored to render the various terms in somewhat different ways, for example, ἐξουσία as ‘authority’; δύναμις as ‘power’; κυριότης as ‘ruler’; and phrases such as τὰ πνευματικὰ τῆς πονηρίας ἐν τοῖς ἐπουρανίοις as ‘wicked spiritual forces in the heavenly world.’ In a number of languages, however, there are simply not enough terms to designate various kinds of powers, authorities, and forces which could be employed in speaking of such supernatural impersonal powers. Accordingly, some translators have simply used a phrase such as ‘any and all kinds of supernatural powers.’ Where it is possible to make certain lexical distinctions between terms and phrases, this, of course, should be done, but in a number of contexts this may be impossible, and accordingly, some explanation in a marginal note may be required if the reader is to understand satisfactorily the intent of the passages in question.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04900102100018</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>05100101600044</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>