<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="003362000000000" Lemma="μύλος" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="true" AlphaPos="μ">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G3458</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes/>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="003362001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, m.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="μύλος" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-ου</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <RelatedLemmas>
        <RelatedLemma>
          <Word>μυλικός</Word>
        </RelatedLemma>
        <RelatedLemma>
          <Word>μύλινος</Word>
        </RelatedLemma>
      </RelatedLemmas>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="003362001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="7.68" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Constructions</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Miscellaneous Constructions</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-12-09 14:23:35" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>a construction of two flat stones between which grain was ground into flour by rotating the top stone</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>mill</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>Some mills were relatively small and operated by hand and could well be considered as artifacts. Others, however, were quite large, and animals were used to rotate the upper stone.|In almost all parts of the world grain is ground in one way or another. Quite frequently mills are of the same general structure as those used in ancient times, in which two relatively large, round, flat stones were placed one on top of the other, and the grain was ground between the two stones. Grain entered the mill through a round hole in the upper stone, and the flour gradually emerged from around the edges of the two stones. In other parts of the world, however, grain is prepared by means of grinding stones called metates. In still other parts of the world, a mortar and pestle are used for the grinding or preparation of grain. In most contexts, what is important is either the large size of the stones or the function of grinding grain, not necessarily the particular form. However, in contexts which speak about tying a millstone to a man’s neck (see {D:7.69}) and his being thrown into the depths of the sea, it is important to refer to relatively large stones which would cause a person to sink immediately. In such a context the use of a term for ‘mortar,’ especially one of wood, would hardly be appropriate since it would normally float. Frequently μύλος may be rendered as ‘stones for grinding grain.’ In other instances, even a more generic expression may be used, for example, ‘a large stone.’</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04002404100010</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>06601802200058</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXLinks>
            <LEXLink>realia:5.10</LEXLink>
          </LEXLinks>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
        <LEXMeaning Id="003362001002000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="7.69" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Constructions</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Miscellaneous Constructions</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-12-09 14:23:35" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>a large, round, flat stone, either upper or lower, used in grinding grain</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>millstone</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>{L:μύλος&lt;SDBG:μύλος:000000&gt;}[a] ‘mill’ ({D:7.68}) denotes a mill as a whole, while μύλος[b] denotes only one of the large flat stones of a mill. For a discussion of some of the translational problems involved in rendering μύλος[b] ‘millstone,’ see the discussion on {L:μύλος&lt;SDBG:μύλος:000000&gt;}[a] ({D:7.68}).</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04001800600034</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04100904200038</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXLinks>
            <LEXLink>realia:5.10</LEXLink>
          </LEXLinks>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>