<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="003413000000000" Lemma="νεφρός" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="true" AlphaPos="ν">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G3510</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes>
    <Note Caller="1" LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="" LastEditedBy="">
      <References/>
      <Content>It would be possible to treat σπλάγχνα[b], κοιλία[c], and νεφρός in this figurative sense in Domain 25 Attitudes and Emotions, but these meanings have been assigned to this domain of Psychological Faculties since the meanings involve aspects of personality which function as agents or presumed locations of psychological dispositions.</Content>
    </Note>
  </Notes>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="003413001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, m.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="νεφρός" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-οῦ</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="003413001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="26.11" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Psychological Faculties</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-12-10 15:55:42" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>(figurative extension of meaning of νεφρός ‘kidney,’ not occurring in its literal meaning in the NT) the psychological faculty of desire, intent, and feeling{N:001}</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>heart</Gloss>
                <Gloss>feelings</Gloss>
                <Gloss>desires</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>Though some persons have attempted to distinguish between σπλάγχνον[b], κοιλία[c], and νεφρός, it is extremely doubtful whether this is really possible or practical. The semantic focus in the use of these terms is clearly the deeper and more intimate feelings and emotions. In some languages one can use a term which literally means ‘belly’ or ‘bowels,’ but more often than not, these emotions are associated with some particular organ of the body such as heart, spleen, liver, etc. Rather, however, than attempting to employ a figurative expression which may or may not be fully equivalent, it is often preferable to refer to the emotional content by using terms such as ‘feelings,’ ‘intents,’ ‘desires,’ or ‘compassion,’ depending upon the context.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>06600202300036</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>