<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="003775000000000" Lemma="παράκλητος" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="false" AlphaPos="π">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G3875</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes>
    <Note Caller="1" LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="" LastEditedBy="">
      <References/>
      <Content>The meaning of παράκλητος overlaps considerably with other domains. It certainly involves psychological factors of encouragement and therefore may very well be treated in Domain 25 Attitudes and Emotions. There is also a sense in which παράκλητος inevitably involves some communication, and therefore it may fittingly be analyzed in Domain 33 Communication. The role of intercession has certain legal implications, and accordingly, παράκλητος is justifiably related to legal procedures in Domain 56 Courts and Legal Procedures. It is very rare indeed that any one term in a receptor language will have all of the distinctive features of meaning possessed by παράκλητος, especially in reference to the role of the Holy Spirit (see {D:12.19}).</Content>
    </Note>
  </Notes>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="003775001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, m.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="παράκλητος" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-ου</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <RelatedLemmas>
        <RelatedLemma>
          <Word>καλέω</Word>
        </RelatedLemma>
      </RelatedLemmas>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="003775001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="12.19" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Supernatural Beings and Powers</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Supernatural Beings</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-12-20 13:33:15" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>(a title for the Holy Spirit) one who helps, by consoling, encouraging, or mediating on behalf of</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>Helper</Gloss>
                <Gloss>Encourager</Gloss>
                <Gloss>Mediator</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>The principal difficulty encountered in rendering παράκλητος is the fact that this term covers potentially such a wide area of meaning. The traditional rendering of ‘Comforter’ is especially misleading because it suggests only one very limited aspect of what the Holy Spirit does. A term such as ‘Helper’ is highly generic and can be particularly useful in some languages. In certain instances, for example, the concept of ‘Helper’ is expressed idiomatically, for example, ‘the one who mothers us’ or, as in one language in Central Africa, ‘the one who falls down beside us,’ that is to say, an individual who upon finding a person collapsed along the road, kneels down beside the victim, cares for his needs, and carries him to safety.|A rendering based upon the concept of legal advocate seems in most instances to be too restrictive. Furthermore, there may be quite unsatisfactory connotations associated with any word which suggests a lawyer, especially since in so many societies, a lawyer is thought of primarily as one who ‘bribes the judges’ or ‘can speak two truths’ or, as in one language, is ‘a professional liar.’ See also παράκλητος {D:35.16} and especially its footnote.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04301401600014</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04301402600006</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04301502600008</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04301600700034</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
        <LEXMeaning Id="003775001002000" IsBiblicalTerm="Y" EntryCode="35.16" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Help, Care For</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Help</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2021-12-20 13:33:15" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>(derivative of παρακαλέω ‘to call upon to provide help,’ not occurring in this specific sense in the NT) one who may be called upon to provide help or assistance{N:001}</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>helper</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments/>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>06200200100026</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>