<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<Lexicon_Entry Id="005229000000000" Lemma="φέγγος" Version="0" HasAramaic="false" InLXX="true" AlphaPos="φ">
  <StrongCodes>
    <Strong>G5338</Strong>
  </StrongCodes>
  <Authors/>
  <AlternateLemmas/>
  <MainLinks/>
  <Notes>
    <Note Caller="1" LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="" LastEditedBy="">
      <References/>
      <Content>It is possible that there is some contrast between φῶς[a] and φέγγος in that φῶς may suggest a somewhat stronger source of light, since φῶς is so frequently associated with the light of the sun while φέγγος is typically related to the light of the moon. In contexts outside the Scriptures there are, however, a number of instances in which there seems to be considerable overlapping of meaning.</Content>
    </Note>
  </Notes>
  <ContributorNote/>
  <BaseForms>
    <BaseForm Id="005229001000000">
      <PartsOfSpeech>
        <PartOfSpeech>noun, n.</PartOfSpeech>
      </PartsOfSpeech>
      <Inflections>
        <Inflection Lemma="φέγγος" BaseFormIndex="1">
          <Form/>
          <Realizations>
            <Realization>-ους</Realization>
          </Realizations>
          <Comments/>
        </Inflection>
      </Inflections>
      <BaseFormLinks/>
      <LEXMeanings>
        <LEXMeaning Id="005229001001000" IsBiblicalTerm="M" EntryCode="14.36" Indent="0">
          <LEXDomains>
            <LEXDomain>Physical Events and States</LEXDomain>
          </LEXDomains>
          <LEXSubDomains>
            <LEXSubDomain>Light</LEXSubDomain>
          </LEXSubDomains>
          <LEXSenses>
            <LEXSense LanguageCode="en" LastEdited="2022-05-09 08:09:01" LastEditedBy="">
              <DefinitionLong/>
              <DefinitionShort>light, in contrast with darkness ({L:σκότος&lt;SDBG:σκότος:000000&gt;}[a], {L:σκοτία&lt;SDBG:σκοτία:000000&gt;}[a], {D:14.53}), usually in relationship to some source of light such as the sun, moon, fire, lamp, etc.{N:001}</DefinitionShort>
              <Glosses>
                <Gloss>light</Gloss>
              </Glosses>
              <Comments>Terms for ‘light’ often differ on the basis of whether there is a specific source of light, for example, a fire, lamps, sun, moon, etc., or whether the light is simply generalized, in the sense of daylight apart from the actual shining of the sun (for example, as in the interior of a room). Some languages also make distinctions between terms for light depending on whether the light comes from a fire or lamp or from a heavenly body.|In a number of languages there is no noun for ‘light,’ but only verbs are employed, since the fact of light is spoken of as something which happens and is hence regarded as an event.</Comments>
            </LEXSense>
          </LEXSenses>
          <LEXReferences>
            <LEXReference>04002402900036</LEXReference>
            <LEXReference>04101302400038</LEXReference>
          </LEXReferences>
          <LEXVideos/>
        </LEXMeaning>
      </LEXMeanings>
    </BaseForm>
  </BaseForms>
</Lexicon_Entry>